Guide to the John Backhouse Papers, 1740-1956
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Backhouse papers 1740-1956
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Backhouse, John, 1784-1845.
Extent: 4,480 Items
Merchant and British Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Business and personal correspondence of the Backhouse family, principally of John Backhouse. Material for the 18th and early 19th centuries reflects the family's mercantile operations, including efforts to collect pre-Revolutionary debts in America. Other papers relate to Backhouse's career as Commissioner and Receiver General of the Excise Office and Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, his service as private secretary to George Canning, his service with the diplomatic corps, his art collection, and his mercantile associates in Amsterdam and Hamburg. Other subjects include the Board of Control under Canning, and the British consulates at Canton and Amoy. Family correspondence contains numerous references to the Foreign Office and to relations with Circassia, France, Greece, Russia, Turkey, and the United States. Letters and diaries of Backhouse's son, George, and his wife include references to the slave trade and describe their life in Havana while he was commissary judge there.
backhousejohn
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Backhouse Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1968.
Biographical Note
Merchant and British Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.
Collection Overview
Business and personal correspondence of the Backhouse family, principally of John Backhouse. Material for the 18th and early 19th centuries reflects the family's mercantile operations, including efforts to collect pre-Revolutionary debts in America. Other papers relate to Backhouse's career as Commissioner and Receiver General of the Excise Office and Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, his service as private secretary to George Canning, his service with the diplomatic corps, his art collection, and his mercantile associates in Amsterdam and Hamburg. Other subjects include the Board of Control under Canning, and the British consulates at Canton and Amoy. Family correspondence contains numerous references to the Foreign Office and to relations with Circassia, France, Greece, Russia, Turkey, and the United States. Letters and diaries of Backhouse's son, George, and his wife include references to the slave trade and describe their life in Havana while he was commissary judge there.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Backhouse, John, 1784-1845; Backhouse, George Canning; Canning, George, 1770-1827; Slave trade -- Cuba; Merchants -- Great Britain -- Correspondence; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- 19th century; Great Britain -- Commerce -- United States
Contents of Collection
- John Backhouse Papers, 1740-1956, (30 boxes, 1 oversize folder)
  - Papers, 1740-1813 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1814-1820 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1821-1822 (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1822 Aug.-1825 (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1826-1827 Aug. (Box 5)
  - Papers, 1827 Sept.-1830 (Box 6)
  - Papers, 1831-1833 July (Box 7)
  - Papers, 1833 Aug.-1835 June (Box 8)
  - Papers, 1835 July-1837 March (Box 9)
  - Papers, 1837 April-1838 May (Box 10)
  - Papers, 1838 June-1839 (Box 11)
  - Papers, 1840-1841 (Box 12)
  - Papers, 1842-1843 (Box 13)
  - Papers, 1844 (Box 14)
  - Papers, 1845-1846 (Box 15)
  - Papers, 1847-1852 Aug. (Box 16)
  - Papers, 1852 Sept.-1855 Sept. (Box 17)
  - Papers, 1855 Oct.-1864 (Box 18)
  - Papers, 1865-1875 (Box 19)
  - Papers, 1876-1877 Oct. (Box 20)
  - Papers, 1877 Nov.-1899 (Box 21)
  - Papers, 1900-1942 (Box 22)
  - Papers, Undated (Box 23)
  - Journal of Ellen Backhouse (Box 24)
  - Miscellany: Genealogy
  - Miscellany: Valentines
  - Wax Seals
  - Miscellaneous Papers
  - Newspapers, printed material (Box 25)
  - Clippings & Pipe Office Roll (Box 26)
  - Volumes (Box 27)
  - Photographs (Box 28)
  - Collection of Autographs, cards, invitations, etc. (Box 29)
  - Papers, 1835-1837 (Box 1 (Sm. Brit. Additions))
  - Papers, Oversize (Opaperfolder 1)